DANIEL BERNIER

OVERVIEW

I'm a software engineer who values healthy teams, diverse perspectives, and legible systems. In prose and code, clear writing is worth the effort. I'm comfortable both learning and teaching, and I'm looking to team with intellectual humility where people enjoy working together. I'm motivated most by the impact I have on the world and the people I meet.

Relevant Skills

Bridging between stakeholders and engineers. Mentoring, pair programming, agile methods. Distributed teams since 2013, fully remote since 2017. Safely reviving legacy systems and untested codebases. Architecture, (micro)services, APIs. Automated testing. Ruby, Rails, GraphQL. Postgresql, MySQL, MongoDB. Generative art. Prior: JavaScript, HTML, CSS. C#, Java, SQL Server, XML.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Engineer at Daylight, July 2022 - present

2022's volatile VC market pushed Daylight to lay off half the team just before I started, and they pivoted to a greenfield product to be built in 20 waterfall weeks. While gelling with the team as quickly as I could, I led the design and build of the new product's graphql backend, and coordinated engineering with product, leadership, and agency staff.

Senior Staff Engineer at Continuity/Mitratech, September 2021 - June 2022

When Mitratech acquired Continuity in December 2021, they were eager to release a large project to GA to show progress. Continuity had reimagined the brains of their flagship product and it was in early-access, but it was immature...and the engineers had exit dates. I helped the new leadership weigh the risks, and we decided I should winterize the application, deleting dead code and streamlining outdated flexibilities, so incoming junior engineers could keep it running until a new product owner was found.

Senior Engineer at Smile Identity, April 2021 - September 2021

Senior Backend Engineer at TED Conferences, January 2017 - March 2021

As the only backend engineer for ted.com, I maintained ted.com, its RSS feed, a custom headless CMS, and identity-related microservices. I built the backend for TED's <u>Series initiative</u> and its <u>Membership program</u>, and their <u>generative avatars</u>.

The website team had different weather than the conferences or back-end tools teams: as the public face of TED, our priorities shifted often, with little notice. I rebuilt portions of the site so non-technical teammates could change content and behavior through github without an engineer. I helped my team make ted.com nimble or solid, depending on how much we knew about what we were trying to do.

Senior Software Engineer at Continuity, November 2013 - December 2016

While working on Continuity Control, an application for banks and credit unions to stay in compliance with federal regulations, I helped grow the team to ten developers. We pair-programmed and mentored junior developers on software design and testing, architecture, project management, and agile methods. We shipped features consistently, made the application more performant and maintainable, and contributed to open source projects we used.

Developer at SeeClickFix, September 2011 - November 2013

I joined a start-up team hoping to mature, and introduced them to agile, pair programming, and object-oriented design. Together, we improved code quality, added unit tests, and improved the performance of seeclickfix.com's public site and private municipal integrations.

Senior Developer at Evolution 1, March 2008 - August 2011

Evolution 1 sold a SaaS tool to employers to configure debit cards for their employees' FSAs and HRAs, and audit purchases made with the debit cards. I was part of the self-organized team of engineers; we practiced Scrum, wrote unit tests, and steadily improved the system architecture with object-oriented and domain-driven design in .Net technologies.

Developer at Software Impressions, May 2006 – February 2008

I mentored the team in object-oriented programming, unit testing, and refactoring, and taught them about automated builds, code generation, and domain-specific languages. We built localizable tools for companies to track ethics violations.

Developer at The Hartford, February 2002 – May 2006

I worked on the Enterprise Business Center, a portal for business insurance brokers to provide quotes from The Hartford.

Developer at Aetna Financial Services, ING Group, January 2000 - December 2001

I maintained content at aetnafinancial.com and ingafs.com.

COMMUNITY

I organized the Hartford Ruby Brigade from 2009-2010, and joined the organizing team of NewHaven.rb in 2012. In 2013 I co-founded NewHaven.io, and in 2015, as its board member, I participated in the first national Tech Meetup at the White House.

EDUCATION

B.S. in Computer Science, May 2006 Central Connecticut State University